All right, we're going to see if I get to
keep my geek card here.
Yes. Okay. Today, I want to talk about the
evolution of technology and how backward
compatibility is essential for growth.
Technologies are in a constant state of
change and they're always adding new
features and and enhanced functionality to
meet growing demands. The three phones
that you see here are a perfect
illustration of this. They represent the
dramatic evolution of the simple telephone
over just the last 30 years from a device
tethered to a wall, to a portable gadget
for calls and eventually text messages, to
the powerful computer we all carry in our
pockets now. The infrastructure to support
the corded and the corded and smartphones
are still in place today, but the first
generation of mobile devices no longer
function. This progression is a familiar
story, but it holds important lessons for
the future of other technologies,
including digital identity. And the
progress shown here is not always
guaranteed. So I want to talk about two
ubiquitous internet technologies that we
all use every day but don't think about.
Some of you may not even know these exist.
But they were both introduced around 30
years ago and their paths to adoption have
been significantly different. The first is
IPv6 and was introduced in December of
1995 and it's so foundational to the
internet that it's literally called the
internet protocol. IPv6 is the successor
to the original internet protocol and it
has struggled to gain traction only
reaching about 50% market share today
despite decades of effort and superior
capabilities. Second technology is 802.11
also known as Wi-Fi. It was first
introduced and standardized in 1997. And
then Wi-Fi has been a massive success.
It's seen seven major releases, each one
faster and more capable than the last and
has become an indispensable part of our
daily lives. So why the difference in
adoption? Backward compatibility. Wi-Fi
was designed from the ground up to be
backward compatible. Each new generation
of Wi-Fi routers and devices could still
communicate with the older ones. This
created a smooth seamless upgrade path for
everyone. IPv6 however was not backward
compatible with its predecessor. This
meant that the transition required a
complete and often costly overhaul of
network infrastructure. This major
difference is the primary reason why Wi
-Fi's adoption has progressed so smoothly
while IPv6's adoption has been a long slow
struggle. Another way to allow for
continuous improvement of technologies is
to ensure compatibility with alternative
standards. To illustrate this, think of
the audio codecs that power our digital
music and podcasts. Many different
standards like FLAC, MPEG, and OPUS
coexist today. For the vast majority of
us, the complex process of encoding and
decoding audio is completely transparent.
We just push play. Each codec is optimized
for a specific situation, whether it's
streaming high fidelity music or ensuring
a clear voice call over a weak connection.
While this isn't ideal, the ecosystem
works because applications have the
ability to handle the different types of
audio files, seamlessly switching codecs
as needed. New codecs can be added to the
ecosystem while old ones are eventually
retired.
So just like these other technologies,
digital identity is at a crossroads. We
have a mix of established legacy systems
and emerging innovative solutions. The
challenge is figuring out how to move
forward without immediately abandoning the
significant investments we've already made
and without destroying the user experience
or preventing progress. A core principle
of the SEDI framework is to support
backward compatibility. We believe the
only viable path forward is one that
embraces interoperability with existing
options without being confined by them.
This approach will allow organizations to
continue using their existing investments
and infrastructure while providing a clear
path to upgrade to newer, more secure and
more capable technologies over time. It
ensures that progress doesn't require
starting from scratch or forcing adoption
of a single solution across the ecosystem.
To show you what this looks like in
practice, we're going to do live demos. We
realize the risk in that. So, I'm pleased
to introduce the participants for our
technical demonstrations today and I'll
invite them to start coming up on the
stage here. In the upcoming demos for this
session and later this afternoon, they'll
showcase how several of the currently
available identity technologies can be
used together in a cohesive and
interoperable ecosystem. While no
technologies for SEDI have been chosen,
they will present possible scenarios
utilizing several different technologies
working together for the first time.
You'll notice how the user experience is
similar despite differences in the
underlying technologies. So if you could
start making your way to the stage as I as
I introduce you. First we have Spruce ID.
They're a US-based company whose mission
is to give people control over their
identity and data across all digital
interactions. Here you go, Wayne. Wayne
Chang is here and their software powers
secure standards-based credentials such as
mobile drivers licenses and verifiable
digital credentials that can be used both
online and in person across government and
enterprise services. As a leader in the
decentralized identity and credential
interoperability space Spruce's technology
supports selective disclosure
unlinkability and no phone home
verification. Their work with states,
federal agencies and standards bodies
demonstrates how digital identity can
enhance access to services, strengthen
security and preserve user autonomy in a
connected world. GET Group North America
is a US-based company specializing in
identity management solutions with over 40
years of experience supporting governments
worldwide and has been a leader in digital
identity since 2017. GET was selected to
deploy the technology for Utah's mobile
driver's license in 2021, helping Utah
citizens securely share their MDL details,
prove their age, and maintain their
privacy. The company has worked with
government agencies and businesses to
accept and verify MDLs, including the TSA,
Utah Highway Patrol, UCCU, and AFCU credit
unions. And then last, they'll be
presenting later, but their technology is
used in the demonstrations. The Cardano
Foundation is a not-for-profit
organization based in Switzerland which
promotes the education development and
adoption of decentralized technologies to
build future-proof industry solutions.
Veridian is an open source digital
identity platform developed by the
foundation that delivers secure enterprise
-ready verification services which protect
user data and prevent fraud. Veridian's
credential management platform led by
Thomas Mayfield implements self-sovereign
identity for individuals and
organizations. And Veridian's core
objective is to ensure authentic
communications and verifiable identity
protocols are easily accessible to all. So
I want to personally thank all of the
presenters for our technical
demonstrations today. They put this
together in a matter of weeks and we're
really excited to see these technologies
working together for the first time. So
I'll turn the time over to them.